教授：我想大家已经意识到
PROFESSOR: Well, I hope you appreciate that we have
我们介绍了一些真正的魔法
we have inducted you into some real magic,
创造新语言的魔法
the magic of building languages
用来创造全新的语言
really building new languages.
我们学了些什么？
What have we looked at?
我们学习了一门用来操作图片的Escher的语言
We've looked at an Escher picture language.
这门语言由Peter Henderson发明
OK? this language invented by Peter Henderson.
我们还学习了数字逻辑语言
We looked at digital logic language.
以及 我们还学习了查询语言
Let's see.We've looked at the query language.
然而你需要明白的是
And the thing you should realize is,
尽管它们都是“玩具级”的语言
even though these were toy examples,
它们也确实是实用工具的核心
they really are the kernels of really useful things.
比如说
So, for instance,
Escher图片语言
the Escher picture language was taken by
就被MIT的学生Henry Wu拿去
Henry Wu, who's a student at MIT,
开发成了一门实用的电路板布局语言
and developed into a real language for laying out PC boards,
它就是在这些结构上扩展而来
based just on extending those structures.
至于数字逻辑语言
And the digital logic language,
Gerry教授在上课的时候也提到过
Gerry mentioned when he showed it to you,
它被扩展为了一个仿真器的基础
was really extended to be used as the basis for a simulator
用来设计真实的计算机
that was used to design a real computer.
至于查询语言
And the query language,
当然就是Prolog语言的一种核心
of course, is kind of the germ of prolog.
我们构造的这些语言
So we built all of these languages,
全都是用Lisp编写
they're all based on LISP.
很多人问
A lot of people ask
Lisp适合用来解决哪一类问题？
what particular problems is LISP good for solving for?
答案就是
The answer is LISP is not...
Lisp不适合解决任何一类问题
LISP is not good for solving any particular problems.
Lisp擅长的是
What LISP is good for
用它来构造一门合适的语言
is constructing within it the right language
来解决你的问题
to solve the problems you want to solve,
你应该像这样看待Lisp
and that's how you should think about it.
那么既然这些语言都基于Lisp
So all of these languages were based on LISP.
那Lisp又基于什么？
Now, what's LISP based on?
它又从何而来？
Where's that come from?
这个我们也学过
Well, we looked at that too.
我们学过元循环求值器
We looked at the meta-circular evaluator
学习了元循环求值器后 我们说
the meta-circular evaluator and sort of said
Lisp就是基于Lisp的
well, LISP is based on LISP.
而让我们研究它的时候
And when we start looking at that,
我们必须得施展一些真正的魔法 对吧？
we've got to do some real magic, right?
这又是什么意思呢？
So what does that mean, right?
Y算子、不动点
Y operators, and fixed points,
以及这样的一个观念--
and the idea that what this means is
Lisp实际上是一个方程的不动点
that LISP is somehow the fixed-point equation for the
一个通过自身来定义的有趣方程
for this funny set of things which are defined in terms of themselves.
这确实是神奇的魔法
Now, it's real magic.
那么今天 作为魔法的最后一步
Well, today, for a final piece of magic,
我们要把它们通通消除掉
we're going to make all the magic go away.
我们已经知道怎么做了
We already know how to do that.
核心要思想是 将Lisp语言
The idea is, we're going to take the register machine architecture
实现在使用寄存器架构的机器上
and show how to implement LISP on terms of that.
回想一下 寄存器机器的关键之处在于
And, remember, the idea of the register machine is that
机器的一部分是确定且有穷的
there's a fixed and finite part of the machine.
它有一个有穷状态控制器
There's a finite-state controller,
它用特定的硬件去做特定的事情
which dose particular thing with a particular amount of hardware.
其中还有一些运算所需的
There are particular data paths,
特殊数据通路
the operation the machine does
然后 为了实现递归
And then, in order to implement recursion
并且维持无穷的假象
and sustain the illusion of infinity,
还使用了一种称作“栈”的大内存
there's some large amount of memory, which is the stack.
所以如果我们要在寄存器机器上实现Lisp
So, if we implement LISP in terms of a register machine,
那么这个时候
then everything ought to become,
所有的东西都会完全具体化
at this point,completely concrete.
所有的魔法都会消除
All the magic should go away.
这堂课结束时
And, by the end of this talk,
我想让你感觉到
I want you get the feeling
相对于神秘的元循环求值器
that, as opposed to this very mysterious meta-circular evaluator
Lisp求值器是非常具体的东西
that a LISP evaluator really is something that's concrete enough
你甚至可以把它放在手心中
that you can hold in the palm of your hand.
你可以想象一下
You should be able to imagine holding
手里拿着一个Lisp解释器的情景
holding a LISP interpreter there.
好 那我们怎么做呢？
All right, how are we going to do this?
所有的原料都已经齐全
We already have all the ingredients.
上节课Gerry教了你们
See, what you learned last time from Gerry
对一个任意的Lisp过程
is how to take any particular couple of LISP procedures.
如何手动地把它们
and hand-translate them
翻译成在寄存器机器上运行的代码
into something that runs on a register machine.
那么 要在寄存器机器上实现Lisp本身
So, to implement all of LISP on a register machine,
我们只需要
all we have to do
把最关键的过程
is take the particular procedures
也就是元循环求值器
that are the meta-circular evaluator
手工翻译成寄存器机器的代码
and hand-translate them for a register machine.
这就实现了整个Lisp
And that does all of LISP
因此 我们已经清楚了实现的原理
Right? So, in principle, we already know how to do this.
而且实际上 这跟翻译
And, indeed, it's going to be no different, in kind,
递归版的阶乘或递归版的斐波那契数列
from in say recursive factorial
没什么区别
or recursive Fibonacci.
只是它规模更大 代码更多
It's just bigger and there's more of it.
只是包含了更多细节
So it'd just be more details,
但是没有任何新的概念
but nothing really conceptually new.
当我们完成这个以后
And also, when we've done that,
所有的东西都变得明确了
and the thing is completely explicit,
当我们看到如何用一系列的
and we see how to implement LISP
寄存器操作来实现Lisp之后
in terms of the actual sequential register operations,
它就成为了我们整个课程中
that's going to be our final
最明确的Lisp模型
most explicit model of LISP in this course.
回忆一下 这个过程贯穿了整个课程
And, remember, that's a progression through this course.
我们先从代换模型开始
We started out with substitution,
它和代数有点相似
which is sort of like algebra.
然后学习了环境模型
And then we went to the environment model,
它引入了“框架”的概念
which talked about the actual frames
以及框架之间的关联
and how they got linked together.
然后我们在元循环求值器中
And then we made that more concrete
做了更具体的讨论
in the meta-circular evaluator.
但是有的事情
There are things
元循环求值器没有告诉我们
the meta-circular evaluator doesn't tell us.
你应该认识到这点
You should realize that.
比如说 我们还不知道
For instance, it left unanswered the question
像这里的递归阶乘过程
of how a procedure, like recursive factorial here,
为何不断地申请新的空间
somehow takes space that grows.
另一方面
On the other hand,
一个语法上看起来像是递归的过程
a procedure which also looks syntactically recursive,
比如FACT-ITER 并不占用栈空间
called fact-iter, somehow doesn't take space.
我们通过代换模型来证明
We justify that it doesn't need to take space
它不占用空间
by showing the substitution model.
但我们并没有说清楚
But we didn't really say
机器是如何做到这一点的
how it happens that the machine manages to do that,
这涉及到一些细节
that that has to do with the details
比如参数是如何传递给过程的
of how arguments are passed to procedures
这是我们在元循环求值器中
And that's the thing we didn't see
没有看到的
in the meta-circular evaluator
完全是因为在所实现的Lisp中
precisely because the way arguments
把参数传递给过程的方式
got passed to procedures in this LISP
取决于
depended on
外部Lisp的传参方式
the way arguments got passed to procedures in this LISP.
但现在 这一点将变得非常明确
But, now, that's going to become extremely explicit.
好
OK.
在开始研究求值器之前
Well, before going on to the evaluator,
我先让你们感受一下
let me just give you a sense of
一个完整Lisp系统是怎么样的
what a whole LISP system looks like
这样你就可以知道 我们要讨论哪部分
so you can see the parts we're going to talk about
不讨论哪些部分
and the parts we're not going to talk about.
首先 这里有一个快乐的Lisp用户
Let's see, over here is a happy LISP user,
他正在和一个叫做读取器的东西交流
and the LISP user is talking to something called the reader.
读取器的工作是
The reader's job in life
读取用户输入的字符串
is to take characters from the user
把它们转化成一种称作
and turn them into data structures
表结构内存的数据结构
in something called a list structure memory.
读取器会读取--
All right, so the reader is going to take
你敲出来的符号、括号
symbols, parentheses,
A和B、1和3这些东西
and A's and B's, and 1s and 3s that you type in,
并把它们变成表结构
and turn these into actual list structure:
变成序对、指针等等
pairs, and pointers, and things.
所以当求值器运行的时候
And so, by the time evaluator is going,
环境里已经不存在原始字符了
there are no characters in the world.
当然 在更现代的Lisp系统中
And, of course, in more modern Lisp systems, there's
可能还有一大团东西
there's sort a big morass here
存在于在读取器和用户之间
that might sit between the user and the reader:
最顶层首先是视窗系统
you know, Windows systems, in top levels,
以及鼠标之类的东西
and mice, and all kinds of things.
但从概念上来说 都是在输入字符
But conceptually, characters are coming in.
总之 读取器把它们都变成指针
All right, the reader transforms these into pointers
指向内存中的对象
pointers to stuff in this memory,
这是求值器的所能看到的东西
and that's what the evaluator sees
明白吗？
OK?
求值器有一些辅助函数
The evaluator has a bunch of helpers.
包括你需要的所有基本运算
It has all possible primitive operators you might want.
也就是说这里另有一盒子东西
So there's a completely separate box,
像一个浮点单元
a floating point unit,
或者其它类似的东西来执行这些运算
or all sorts of things, which do the primitive operators.
如果你想要更多的基本操运算
there's and, if you want more special primitives,
你就实现更多的运算符
you build more primitive operators,
但它们和求值器都是分离的
but they're separate from the evaluator.
求值器最终算出结果
The evaluator finally gets an answer
并且把它们告诉打印程序
and communicates that to the printer.
现在 打印程序的任务就是
And now, the printer's job in life
从求值器取得这个表结构
is this list structure coming from the evaluator,
再把它们变回字符
and turn it back into characters,
然后通过某种界面
and communicate them to the user through
展示给用户
whatever interface there is.
那么 今天我们要讨论的是这个求值器
OK. Well, today, what we're going to talk about is this evaluator.
基本运算和Lisp没有什么特别的关系
The primitive operators have nothing particular to do with LISP,
它们只取决于你怎么实现基本运算
they're however you like to implement primitive operations.
读取器和打印程序实际上很复杂
The reader and printer are actually complicated,
但是我们不去讨论它们
but we're not going to talk about them.
从字符构建列表的过程中
They sort of have to do with details of how you might build
它们需要处理很多细节
build up list structure from characters.
说来话长
So that is a long story,
我们就不讨论它了
but we're not going to talk about it,
关于表结构内存
the list structure memory,
我们下次再来讨论
we'll talk about next time.
那么去除了读取和打印的细节
So, pretty much, except for the details of reading and printing,
关于这个求值器
the only mystery that's going to be left
所剩下的唯一谜团
after you see the evaluator
几乎就只有怎么在传统内存上构建表结构了
is how you build list structure on conventional memories.
不过我们把那也放到下次来讨论
But we'll worry about that next time too.
好
OK.
那么 我们先来看看这个求值器
Well, let's start talking about the evaluator.
我将要展示的这个求值器
The one that we're going to show you,
我想 它并没有什么特别的
of course, is not, I think, nothing special about it.
它只是一台专门运行Lisp的寄存器机器
It's just a particular register machine that runs LISP.
它有七个寄存器
And it has seven registers,
这是它的七个寄存器
and here are the seven registers.
这个寄存器叫EXP
There's a register, called EXP
它的任务是存放
and its job is to hold
将要被求值的表达式
the expression to be evaluated.
具体来说
And by that, I mean
它存放的是一个指针
it's going to hold a pointer
指针指向存放着求值的表达式
to someplace in list structure memory
的一处表结构内存
the expression to be evaluated.
还有一个叫做ENV的寄存器
There's a register, called ENV,
它存放着环境
which holds the environment
也就是表达式的求值环境
in which this expression is to be evaluated.
同样的 这也是一个指针
And, again, I made a pointer.
环境是一种数据结构
The environment is some data structure.
这个叫做FUN的寄存器--
There's a register, called FUN, which will
当你在应用一个过程时
which will hold the procedure to be applied
它会存放这个过程
when you go to apply a procedure.
还有寄存器ARGL
A register, called ARGL,
它存放的是已求值的参数
which holds the list of evaluated arguments.
从这里开始你能看到
What you can start seeing here is
求值器的基本构造
the basic structure of the evaluator.
回忆一下它是怎么工作的
Remember how evaluators work.
对这一块输入表达式和环境
There's a piece that takes expressions and environments,
而这一块接收函数
and there's a piece that takes functions
或者说 过程以及参数
or procedures and arguments.
EVAL-APPLY循环使用这些寄存器工作
And going back and forth around here is the eval/apply loop.
所以这些是EVAL-APPLY的基本组成部分
So those are the basic pieces of the eval and apply.
还有一些别的东西 比如CONTINUE寄存器
Then there's some other things, there's continue.
你之前已经见过CONTINUE寄存器
You just saw before how the continue register is used to
是如何实现递归以及栈操作的
implement recursion and stack discipline.
还有个寄存器用来存放
There's a register that's going to hold the
某个求值的结果
result of some evaluation.
然后 除了这些以外
And then, besides that,
还有一个临时寄存器
there's one temporary register,
它就是UNEV
called UNEV,
一般来讲 在求值器中
which typically, in the evaluator,
它是用来存放正在求值的表达式
is going to be used to hold temporary pieces of the
的临时部分
expression you're working on,
就是那些尚未求值的部分
which you haven't gotten around to evaluate yet
那么 这就是我的七寄存器机器
Right? So there's my machine: a seven-register machine.
当然 你可能想造一台
And, of course, you might want to make a machine with
有更多寄存器的机器 来取得更好性能
a lot more registers to get better performance,
但我们这个只是一台小型机器
but this is just a tiny, minimal one.
那么数据通路呢？
Well, how about the data paths?
这台机器有很多专为Lisp设计的运算
This machine has a lot of special operations for LISP.
这里有几条典型的数据通路
So, here are some typical data paths.
其中一条可能是
A typical one might be,
将EXP寄存器的值赋给VAL寄存器
oh, assign to the VAL register the contents of the EXP register.
用我们之前的数据通路图来说
That's in terms of those diagrams you saw,
就是一条箭头上的小按钮
that's a little button on some arrow.
这还有一个更复杂的
Here's a more complicated one.
它判断
It says branch,
如果EXP寄存器的内容是COND语句
if the thing in the expression register is a conditional
那么这里就会跳转到EV-COND标号处
to some label here, called the ev-conditional.
你可以想象出很多种实现它的方法
And you can imagine this implemented in a lot of different ways.
你可以把这个判断看作是
You might imagine this conditional test
一个特殊意图的子过程
as a special purpose sub-routine,
而条件被表示成某种数据抽象
and conditional might be represented as some data abstraction
你在这个层面上不用考虑它
that you don't care about at this level of detail.
那么它可以用子过程实现
So that might be done as a sub-routine.
如果机器通过硬件来判断表达式类型
This might be a machine with hardware-types,
那么某些特定比特就代表了COND语句
and conditional might be testing some bits for a particular code.
有很多种实现办法
There are all sorts of ways that's
它们都低于我们关注的这一层抽象
beneath the level of abstraction we're looking at.
然后还有另一种操作
Another kind of operation,
以及其它很多操作
and there are a lot of different operations
把EXP的第一个子句赋值给EXP
assigned to EXP, the first clause of what's in EXP.
这可能是处理COND语句的一部分
This might be part of processing a conditional.
同样 FIRST-SELECTOR这个选择子
And, again, first clause is some selector
我们也不需要关心它的细节
whose details we don't care about.
同样可以把那也看成一个子过程
And you can, again, imagine that as a sub-routine
用来进行一些表操作
which'll do some list operations,
或者你也可以想象成
or you can imagine that as
一个直接构建在硬件中的东西
something that's built directly into hardware.
我之所以强调
The reason I keep saying you can imagine it
你可以把它想象成硬件直接实现
built directly into hardware
是因为尽管有很多的运算
is even though there are a lot of operations,
但也它们的数量也是固定的
there are still a fixed number of them.
我记不清有多少 大概有150个
I forget how many, maybe 150.
所以假设用硬件实现它们是合理的
So, it's plausible to think of building these directly into hardware.
而这一条更加复杂
Here's a more complicated one.
你会发现 这条涉及到
You can see this has to do with
查找变量的值
looking up the values of variables.
它会查找某条表达式中
It says assign to the VAL register
某个变量的值
the result of looking up the variable value
并赋值给VAL寄存器
of some particular expression,
在本例中 也就是
which, in this case, is supposed to be
在某个环境中查找变量
a variable in some environment.
然后这个操作
And this'll be some operation
会搜索整个环境结构
that search through the environment structure,
无论环境是如何表示的
however it is represented,
并查找该变量
and goes and looks up that variable.
同样 它也不在我们思考的
And, again, that's below the level of detail
的抽象层面上
that we're thinking about.
它需要处理的细节是
This is... this has to do with the details of
用来表示环境的数据结构
the data structures for representing environments.
但是不管怎么说 这就是这个寄存器机器的
But, anyway, there is this fixed and finite number
有穷数量的固定操作
of operations in the register machine.
那么 它的整体结构是什么样子的？
Well, what's its overall structure?
这有几个典型的运算
Those are some typical operations.
想一想 我们要做什么
Remember what we have to do,
我们需要把元循环求值器
we have to take the meta-circular evaluator--
这就是元循环求值器的一部分
and here's a piece of the meta-circular evaluator.
这是书中使用抽象代码的版本
This is the one using abstract syntax that's in the book.
它和Gerry教授给你们展示的有些不同
It's a little bit different from the one that Gerry shows you.
关于求值器
And the main thing
主要需要记住的是
to remember about the evaluator is that
它是某种针对表达式类型的分情况分析
it's doing some sort of case analysis on the kinds of expressions:
看它是否为自求值的 或被引用的
so if it's either self-evaluated, or quoted,
或是别的什么
or whatever else.
而在大部分情况下
And then, in the general case where
它处理的是一个过程应用
the expression it's looking at is an application,
那么里面有一些技巧性的递归过程
there's some tricky recursions going on.
首先 EVAL要调用它自己
First of all, eval has to call itself
来求值运算符以及
both to evaluate the operator
所有的运算对象
and to evaluate all the operands.
因此这些标红线的地方
So there's this sort of red recursion
就是某种在语法树上的递归
of values walking down the tree
这是很简单的递归
that's sort of the easy recursion.
只是EVAL在递归地遍历语法树
That's just eval walking down this tree of expressions.
然后在求值器中 有一个复杂的递归
Then, in the evaluator, there's a hard recursion.
由绿线到红线的递归
There's the red to green.
由EVAL调用APPLY
Eval calls apply.
也就是把过程调用
That's the case where evaluating a procedure argument
归约为了 将过程应用在
reduces to applying the procedure
实参表上
to the list of arguments.
然后请看APPLY
And then, apply comes over here.
APPLY需要过程PROC和参数ARGS
Apply takes a procedure and arguments
一般情况下
and, in the general case
PROC都是一个复合过程
where there's a compound procedure,
随着APPLY不断被调用
apply goes around and
绿线处会调用红线处
green calls red.
APPLY被调用并再次调用EVAL
Eval-- Apply comes around and calls eval again.
EVAL会求值过程体
Eval's the body of the procedure
基于一个扩展了的环境
in the result of extending the environment
这个环境通过将过程的形式参数
with the parameters of the procedure
与实际参数绑定起来而得
by binding the arguments.
而对于最基本的情况
Except in the primitive case,
它会调用PRIMITIVE-APPLY过程
where it just calls something else primitive-apply
而那又不是求值器的工作了
which is not really the business of the evaluator.
那么像这样从红到绿
So this sort of red to green,
又到红又到绿
to red to green,
这就是EVAL-APPLY循环
Right? That's the that's the eval/apply loop,
这就是我们在求值器中
and that's the thing that we're going to want to see
想要看到的东西
in the evaluator.
这样 你不会惊异于
Well, it won't surprise you at all that
这个求值器的两大部分
the two big pieces of this evaluator
对应于EVAL-APPLY
are correspond to eval and apply.
一个部分叫EVAL-DISPATCH
There's a piece called eval-dispatch,
还有一部分叫做APPLY-DISPATCH
and a piece called apply-dispatch.
在我们关注代码细节之前
And, before we get into the details of the code,
理解它们的方法就是
the way to understand this is to think,
假设这些求值器的各个部分
again, in terms of these pieces of evaluator
和这个世界中其它的部分有一些约定
having contracts with the rest of the world.
在进入这些肮脏的细节前
What do they do from the outside
它们在外部做了什么？
before getting into the grungy details?
针对EVAL-DISPATCH的约定
Well, the contract for eval-dispatch--
还记得吗 它对应的是EVAL
remember, it corresponds to eval.
它要在环境中求值一个表达式
It's got to evaluate an expression in an environment.
那么 这部分要做的就是
So, in particular, what this one is going to do,
EVAL-DISPATCH会假设当你调用它的时候
eval-dispatch will assume that, when you call it,
你想要求值的表达式
that the expression you want to evaluate
就存放在EXP寄存器中
is in the EXP register.
而求值所基于的环境
The environment in which you want the evaluation
则存放在ENV环境中
to take place is in the ENV register.
而CONTINUE寄存器用来指示
And continue tells you
当求值完成后
the place where the machine should go next
机器需要去向何方
when the evaluation is done.
EVAL-DISPATCH的约定实际上就是
Eval-dispatch's contract is that
它会执行实际的求值
it'll actually perform that evaluation,
并且在求值结束后
and, at the end of which,
它会转到由CONTINUE寄存器指定的位置
it'll end up at the place specified by continue.
求值的结果会存放在VAL寄存器中
The result of the evaluation will be in the VAL register.
需要提醒的是
And it just warns you,
它对其余的寄存器
it makes no promises about
不做任何承诺
what happens to rest the registers.
其它所有的寄存器都可能被修改
All other registers might be destroyed.
那么这是一部分
So, there's one piece, OK?
这些部分一块构成了APPLY-DISPATCH
Together, the pieces, apply-dispatch
它们对应了APPLY
that corresponds to apply,
用来把一个过程应用在一些参数上
it's got to apply a procedure to some arguments,
因此它假设ARGL寄存器
so it assumes that this register, ARGL,
存放着求值后的参数列表
contains a list of the evaluated arguments.
FUN寄存器存放着那个过程
FUN contains the procedure.
它们对应于元循环求值器中的
Those correspond to the arguments to
参数应用部分
the apply procedure in the meta-circular evaluator.
在我们的这个求值器中
And apply, in this particular evaluator,
我们APPLY时采用的约定是
we're going to use a discipline which says
当APPLY完成后--
the place that apply
机器应该跳转到
the place the machine should go to next
的下一个地方应该是
when apply is done, is at the moment
APPLY-DISPATCH被调用时的栈顶元素
apply-dispatch is called at the top of the stack
这只是针对这台机器的约定
that's just discipline for the way this particular machine's organized.
现在已经给出了APPLY的所有约定
And now apply's contract is given all that.
它会去执行应用
It'll perform the application.
这个应用的结果将会保存在VAL寄存器中
The result of that application will end up in VAL.
栈会被弹出
The stack will be popped.
同样的
And, again,
其它所有寄存器的内容都可能被修改
the contents of all the other registers may be destroyed.
那么 这就是这台机器的基本结构
All right? So that's the basic organization of this machine.
我们先课间休息一下
Let's break for a little bit and see if there are any questions
然后再来研究一个真实的例子
and then we'll do a real example.
[Music]
现在 我们来研究一下这台寄存器机器
Well, let's take the register machine now,
我们一步一步地跟进
and actually step through,
具体到每一处细节
and really, in real detail,
这样你就能完全具体地看到
so you see completely concrete
表达式是如何求值的
how some expressions are evaluated,
那么我们从一个非常简单的表达式开始
Alright? So, let's start with a very simple expression.
Let's evaluate the expression 1.
我们要求值的表达式只有一个1
And we need an environment, so let's imagine that
我们需要一个环境，所以想象
somewhere there's an environment, we'll call it E,0.
有一个环境，我们叫它E0
And just, since we'll use these later,
而且虽然我们之后要用到
we obviously don't really need anything to evaluate 1.
我们显然并不需要其它的东西来求值1
But, just for reference later, let's assume that E,0 has in it
但是为了之后指代方便，我们假设环境E0中
an X that's bound to 3 and a Y that's bound to 4, OK?
有一个变量X与3绑定，Y与4绑定，好吗
And now what we're going to do is we're going to evaluate 1
现在我们要做的是我们在这个环境中
in this environment, and so the ENV register has a pointer
求值1这个表达式，所以ENV寄存器里有一个指针
to this environment, E,0, all right?
指向这个环境，E0，对吗
So let's watch that thing go.
那么我们来看它怎么进行
What I'm going to do is step through the code.
我要做的是步步跟进代码
And, let's see, I'll be the controller.
大家看，我会作为控制器
And now what I need, since this gets rather complicated,
现在我需要的，虽说这个通常很复杂
is a very little execution unit.
是一个小小的执行单元
So here's the execution unit, OK?
那么请上我们的执行单元，好吗
OK.
好的
All right, now we're going to start.
好，现在我们要开始了
We're going to start the machine at eval-dispatch, right?
我们要从eval-dispatch启动机器，对吗
That's the beginning of this.
那是这个过程的开始
Eval-dispatch is going to look at the expression in dispatch,
eval-dispatch会查看被分发的表达式
just like eval
就像eval
where we look at the very first thing.
最开始在eval里寻找东西
We branch on whether or not this expression is self-evaluating.
我们判断这个表达式是不是自求值的
Self-evaluating is some abstraction we put into the machine--
self-evaluating（自求值）是我们放进机器的一个抽象
it's going to be true for numbers--
它对于数字来说为真
to a place called ev-self-eval, right?
放在一个叫ev-self-eval的地方，对吗
So me, being the controller, looks at ev-self-eval,
那么我，作为控制器，查看ev-self-eval
so we'll go over to there.
所以我们要跳到那里
Ev-self-eval says fine, assign to val
Ev-self-eval说好，给VAL寄存器赋值
whatever is in the expression unit, OK?
把表达式单元（EXP）中的东西赋给它，好吗
And I have a bug
然后我有一个bug
because what I didn't do when I initialized this machine
因为我初始化机器的时候没有做一件事情
is also say what's supposed to happen when it's done,
就是说好完成的时候应该做什么
so I should have started out the machine with
所以我应该在启动机器的时候
done being in the continue register, OK?
让continue寄存器的内容为done，对吗
So we assign to VAL.
所以我们给VAL赋值
And now go to fetch of continue, and now change--
现在取出continue里的东西，并且修改
OK.
好
OK, let's try something harder.
好，我们看一点更难的
Let's reset the machine here,
我们在这里重置机器
and we'll put in the expression register, X, OK?
然后我们要把表达式X放进EXP里
Start again at eval-dispatch.
重新从eval-dispatch开始
Check, is it self-evaluating?
看，它是自求值的吗
No.
不是
Is it a variable?
它是变量吗
Yes.
是的
We go off to ev-variable.
我们执行ev-variable
It says assign to VAL,
它说给VAL赋值
look up the variable value in the expression register, OK?
查询EXP寄存器里变量的值，对吧
Go to fetch of continue.
取出continue的内容
PROFESSOR: Done.
好了
PROFESSOR: OK.
好
All right.
Well, that's the basic idea.
那这是基本的想法
That's a simple operation of the machine.
这是这个机器上一个简单的操作
Now, let's actually do something a little bit more interesting.
现在我们实际做一些有趣一点的事情
Let's look at the expression the sum of x and y.
我们看这个表达式，x和y求和
OK.
好
And now we'll see how you start unrolling these expression trees.
现在我们会看到怎么开始展开表达式树
Well, start again at eval-dispatch.
再次从eval-dispatch开始
Self-evaluating?
是自求值的吗
No.
不是
Variable? No.
是变量吗？不是
All the other special forms which I didn't write down,
其他我没写在这里的所有特殊形式
like quote, and lambda, and set, and whatever,
引用，lambda，集合，其他什么东西
it's none of those.
它全都不是
It turns out to be an application,
那么它是一个过程应用
so we go off to ev-application, OK?
所以我们去到ev-application这里，对吗
Ev-application, remember what it's going to do overall.
记住ev-application需要做什么
It is going to evaluate the operator.
它需要求值操作符
It's going to evaluate the arguments,
它需要求值那些参数
and then it's going to go apply them.
然后它需要应用过程
So, before we start, since we're being very literal,
所以在我们开始之前，为了保持字面上的严谨#TBD
we'd better remember that, somewhere in this environment,
我们最好记住，这个环境的某一个地方
it's linked to another environment in which
链接到了另一个环境
plus is bound to the primitive procedure plus
在那里加号与加法这个基本过程相绑定
before we get an unknown variable in our machine.
以防止我们在机器中拿到一个未知变量#TBD
OK, so we're at ev-application.
好，那么我们看ev-application
OK, assign to UNEV the operands
给UNEV赋值操作数
of what's in the expression register, OK?
EXP寄存器里的东西的操作数，对吗
Those are the operands.
这些是操作数
UNEV's a temporary register where we're going to save them.
UNEV是一个用来保存它们的临时寄存器
PROFESSOR: I'm assigning.
我正在赋值
PROFESSOR: Assign to EXP the operator.
给EXP赋值这个操作符
Now, notice we've destroyed that expression in x,
现在，注意到我们已经销毁了这个关于x的表达式#TBD
but the piece that we need is now in UNEV. OK.
但是我们需要的部分在UNEV中，好
Now, we're going to get set up to recursively evaluate the operator.
现在我们要准备好递归求值这个操作符
Save the continue register on the stack.
把continue寄存器保存在栈上
Save the environment.
保存环境
Save UNEV.
保存UNEV
OK, assign to continue a label called eval-args.
给continue赋值一个叫做eval-args的标签
Now, what have we done?
我们做了什么
We've set up for a recursive call.
我们为递归调用做了必要的准备
We're about to go to eval-dispatch.
我们要开始执行eval-dispatch
We've set up for a recursive call to eval-dispatch.
我们为递归调用eval-dispatch做了准备
What did we do?
我们做了哪些事情
We took the things we're going to need later,
我们把之后要用到的东西
those operands that were in UNEV;
UNEV里面的这些操作数
the environment in which we're going to eventually have to,
还有这个环境，我们最后要在里面
maybe, evaluate those operands;
可能要求值操作数
the place we eventually want to go to, which, in this case, was done;
还有这个我们最后要回到的位置，这个例子里是done
we've saved them on the stack.
我们把这些东西存在了栈上
The reason we saved them on the stack is because
我们把它们存在栈上的原因是
eval-dispatch makes no promises about what registers it may destroy.
eval-dispatch不保证它不会毁坏寄存器
So all that stuff is saved on the stack.
那么所有这些东西都存在了栈上
Now, we've set up eval-dispatch's contract.
现在我们准备好了eval-dispatch的约束
There's a new expression, which is the operator plus;
有一个新的表达式，也就是加法操作符
a new environment, although, in this case, it's the same one;
一个新的环境，尽管在这里和刚才一样
and a new place to go to when you're done, which is eval-args.
和一个新的，完成时要返回的位置，也就是eval-args
So that's set up.
那么我们准备好了
Now, we're going to go off to eval-dispatch.
现在我们来执行eval-dispatch
Here we are back at eval-dispatch.
我们回到了eval-dispatch
It's not self-evaluating.
它不是自求值的
Oh, it's a variable, so we'd better go off to ev-variable, right?
哦，它是一个变量，所以我们最好调用ev-variable，对吧
Ev-variable is assigned to VAL.
给VAL赋值ev-variable
Look up the variable value of the expression, OK?
查询表达式里变量的值
So VAL is the primitive procedure plus, OK?
那么VAL寄存器中应该是加法基本操作
And go to fetch of continue.
然后去读取continue
PROFESSOR: Eval-args.
是eval-args
PROFESSOR: Right, which is now eval-args not done.
对，是现在还没有完成的eval-args
So we come back here at eval-args, and what do we do?
所以我们回到eval-args，我们应该做什么
We're going to restore the stuff that we saved, so we restore UNEV.
我们应该取回我们保存起来的东西，所以我们恢复UNEV
And notice, there, it wasn't necessary, although, in general, it would be.
注意这里，尽管它不是必须的，但是通常来说是，
It might be some arbitrary evaluation that happened.
它可能是发生的任何求值过程
We restore ENV. OK, we assign to FUN fetch of VAL.
我们恢复ENV，好，我们给FUN赋值VAL的值
OK, now, we're going to go off and start evaluating some arguments.
现在我们要开始求值参数
Well, first thing we'd better do is save FUN because some
我们最好先把FUN寄存器保存起来
arbitrary stuff might happen in that evaluation.
因为求值过程中可能发生任何事情
We initialize the argument list. Assign to argl an empty argument list,
我们初始化参数列表，给ARGL赋值一个空的参数列表
and go to eval-arg-loop, OK?
然后调用eval-arg-loop，对吗
At eval-arg-loop, the idea of this is we're going to
在eval-arg-loop这里，它的想法是我们要
evaluate the pieces of the expressions that are in UNEV, one by one,
一个一个地求值UNEV中的表达式的部分
and move them from unevaluated in UNEV
然后把它们从保存未求值表达式的UNEV
to evaluated in the arg list, OK?
移到求值完成的参数列表中，对吗
So we save argl.
那么保存ARGL
We assign to EXP the first operand of the stuff in UNEV.
我们给EXP赋值UNEV里面东西的第一个操作数
Now, we check and see if that was the last operand.
现在我们检查那是不是最后一个
In this case, it is not, all right?
现在它不是，对吧
So we save the environment.
那么我们保存环境
We save UNEV because those are all things we might need later.
我们把UNEV存起来因为里面有我们之后需要的所有东西
We're going to need the environment to do some more evaluations.
我们需要这个环境来执行更多的求值
We're going to need UNEV to look at what the rest of those arguments were.
我们需要UNEV来查询剩下的参数是什么
We're going to assign continue a place called accumulate-args, or accumulate-arg.
我们要给continue赋值一个叫做accumulate-args的东西，或者accumulate-arg
OK, now, we've set up for another call to eval-dispatch, OK?
好，现在我们已经准备好再次调用eval-dispatch了，对吗
All right, now, let me short-circuit this
现在让我们把这个短路掉
so we don't go through the details of eval-dispatch.
这里我们不跟进eval-dispatch的细节
Eval-dispatch's contract says I'm going to end up,
eval-dispatch的约束说我要在结束时
the world will end up, with the value of evaluating this expression
这个世界最终变成，求值这个表达式得到的值
in this environment in the VAL register,
在这个环境中保存在VAL寄存器里
and I'll end up there.
我在这里结束
So we short-circuit all of this, and a 3 ends up in VAL.
那么我们把这些全都短路掉，最后VAL的内容是3
And, when we return from eval-dispatch,
并且当我们从eval-dispatch返回的时候
we're going to return to accumulate-arg.
我们会返回到accumulate-arg这里
PROFESSOR: Accumulate-arg.
accumulate-arg
PROFESSOR: With 3 in the VAL register, OK?
VAL寄存器里是3，对吧
So that short-circuited that evaluation.
求值被短路了
Now, what do we do?
现在我们做什么
We're going to go back and look at the rest of the arguments,
我们返回继续看剩下的参数
so we restore UNEV.
所以我们恢复UNEV
We restore ENV. We restore argl.
恢复ENV，恢复ARGL
One thing.
这件事
PROFESSOR: Oops!
哦
Parity error.
奇偶错误
[LAUGHTER]
（笑声）
PROFESSOR: Restore argl.
恢复ARGL
PROFESSOR: OK.
好的
OK, we assign to argl consing on
好，我们给ARGL cons上一个
fetch of the value register to what's in argl.
把从VAL寄存器中读到的值cons到ARGL上
OK, we assign to UNEV the rest of the operands in fetch of UNEV,
我们给UNEV赋值，从UNEV中读取剩下的操作数
and we go back to eval-arg-loop.
然后我们返回eval-arg-loop
PROFESSOR: Eval-arg-loop.
eval-arg-loop
PROFESSOR: OK.
Now, we're about to do the next argument,
现在我们处理下一个参数
so the first thing we do is save argl.
所以首先我们要保存ARGL
OK, we assign to EXP the first operand of fetch of UNEV.
好，我们给EXP赋值从UNEV里读到的第一个操作数
OK,we test and see if that's the last operand.In this case, it is
我们检查那是不是最后一个操作数，在这里它是的
so we're going to go to a special place that says evaluate the last argument
所以我们跳到一个特殊的地方，它来求值最后一个参数
because, notice,after evaluating the argument,
因为请注意，在求值这个参数之后
we don't need the environment any more.
我们就不再需要这个环境了
That's going to be the difference.
那就是区别
So here, at eval-last-arg,
在这里，在eval-last-arg这里
which is assigned to continue accumulate-last-arg,
continue被赋值了了accumulate-last-arg
now, we're set up again for eval-dispatch.
现在我们再次为eval-dispatch做准备
We've got a place to go to when we're done.
我们有一个完成时要跳到的地方
We've got an expression.
我们有一个表达式
We've got an environment.
我们有一个环境
OK, so we'll short-circuit the call to eval-dispatch.
好，那么我们短路对eval-dispatch的调用
And what'll happen is there's a y there,
现在情况是这里有一个Y
it's 4 in that environment, so VAL will end up with 4 in it.
它在这个环境里是4，所以VAL寄存器最后将会存着4
And, then, we're going to end up at accumulate-last-arg, OK?
那么然后我们要在accumulate-last-arg这里结束了，对吧
So, at accumulate-last-arg, we restore argl.
所以在accumulate-last-arg这里我们恢复ARGL寄存器
We assign to argl cons of fetch of the new value onto it,
我们给ARGL赋值它和读到的新值cons后的结果
so we cons a 4 onto that.
所以我们在那上面cons一个4
We restore what was saved in the function register.
我们恢复保存在函数寄存器（FUN）中的东西
And notice, in this case, it had not been destroyed,
注意在这里它没有被销毁
but in general, it will be.
但是通常来讲它会的
And now, we're ready to go off to apply-dispatch, all right?
现在我们准备好调用apply-dispatch了，对吗
So we've just gone through the eval.
所以我们刚刚步步跟进了eval过程
We evaluated the argument, the operator, and the arguments,
我们求值了参数，操作数和参数列表，
and now, we're about to apply them.
现在我们要应用过程
So we come off to apply-dispatch here, OK?
所以我们来到apply-dispatch这里，好吗
We come off to apply-dispatch,
我们来到apply-dispatch
and we're going to check whether it's a primitive or a compound procedure.
我们要检查它是一个基本过程还是复合过程
PROFESSOR: Yes.
对
PROFESSOR: All right.
好的
So, in this case, it's a primitive procedure,
那么在这种情况下它是一个基本过程
and we go off to primitive-apply.
我们去调用primitive-apply（基本应用）
So we go off to primitive-apply, and it says
那么我们看primitive-apply，它说
assign to VAL the result of applying primitive procedure
给VAL赋值对参数列表应用
of the function to the argument list.
应用函数中的基本过程后的结果
PROFESSOR: I don't know how to add.
我不知道怎么做加法
I'm just an execution unit.
我只是一个执行单元
PROFESSOR: Well, I don't know how to add either.
我也不知道
I'm just the evaluator, so we need a primitive operator.
我只是一个求值器，所以我们需要一个基本操作符
Let's see, so the primitive operator, what's the
我看看，那么这位基本操作符，
What's the sum of 3 and 4?
3+4等于多少？
AUDIENCE: 7.
观众：7
PROFESSOR: OK, 7.
教授：好的，7
PROFESSOR: Thank you.
谢谢
PROFESSOR: Now, we restore continue,
现在我们恢复continue
and we go to fetch of continue.
读取里面的东西
PROFESSOR: Done.
好了
PROFESSOR: OK.
好
Well, that was in as much detail as you will ever see.
这些是你能看到的最细致的过程了
We'll never do it in as much detail again.
我们再也不会讲得这么细了
One very important thing to notice is that
一个很重要的事情是
we just executed a recursive procedure, right?
我们刚刚执行了一个递归过程，是吧
This whole thing, we used a stack
整个东西，我们使用了栈
and the evaluator was recursive.
而且求值器是递归的
A lot of people think the reason that you need a stack
有很多人以为我们在求值器中
and recursion in an evaluator is because you might be
需要栈和递归的理由是你可能
evaluating recursive procedures like factorial or Fibonacci.
会用它求值像阶乘或者斐波那契这样的递归过程
It's not true.
那是错误的
So you notice we did recursion here, and all we evaluated was
你看我们在这里做了递归，而我们求值的只有
plus X, Y, all right?
x加上y，对吧
The reason that you need recursion in the evaluator is
在求值器中需要递归的理由是
because the evaluation process, itself, is recursive, all right?
是因为求值这个过程本身，就是递归的，好吗
It's not because the procedure that you might be evaluating in LISP
而不是因为你要用LISP求值的过程
is a recursive procedure.
可能是一个递归过程
So that's an important thing
所以那是一件很重要的事情
that people get confused about a lot.
人们经常在这里被迷惑
The other thing to notice is that, when we're done here,
另一点要注意的是，我们在这里完成之后，
we're really done.
我们就真的完成了
Not only are we at done, but
不仅完成了，而且
there's no accumulated stuff on the stack, right?
栈上没有堆起来的东西了，对吧
The machine is back to its initial state, all right?
这个机器返回最开始的状态了，是吧
So that's part of what it means to be done.
那就是“完成”的其中一部分意义
Another way to say that is the evaluation process has reduced
从另一个角度来看是，求值过程
the expression, plus X, Y, to the value here, 7.
把+ x y这个表达式归约到了7这个值
And by reduced, I mean a very particular thing.
我说归约（减少），指的是一个特定的事情
It means that there's nothing left on the stack.
那意味着栈上没剩下任何东西了
The machine is now in the same state,
机器现在在与开始相同的状态
except there's something in the value register.
除了VAL寄存器里有一些东西
It's not part of a sub-problem of anything.
它不是任何问题的子问题
There's nothing to go back to.
不需要回到任何步骤
OK.
好
Let's break.
我们休息
Question?
有问题吗
AUDIENCE: The question here, in the stack,
观众：关于栈有一个问题
is because the data may be recursive.
是数据有可能是递归的
You may have embedded expressions, for instance.
例如你可能会遇到嵌套的表达式
PROFESSOR: Yes, because you might have embedded expressions.
教授：是的，因为你可能遇到嵌套的表达式
But, again, don't confuse that
但是再说一遍，不要搞混
with what people sometimes mean by the data may be recursive,
有时候人们说数据是递归的
which is to say you have these list-structured, recursive data list operations.
他们说的是存在这些列表结构的，递归的数据列表操作
That has nothing to do with it.
那和这没有关系
It's simply that the expressions contain sub-expressions.
这只是包含子表达式的表达式而已
Yeah?
嗯
AUDIENCE: Why is it that the order of the arguments in the arg list got reversed?
观众：为什么参数列表中参数的顺序是反过来的
PROFESSOR: Ah! Yes, I should've mentioned that.
教授：啊！是，我应该提到这个的
Here, the reason the order is reversed--
这里顺序反过来的原因是
it's a question of what you mean by reversed.
问题在于你怎么定义“反过来”
I believe it was Newton.
我记得应该是牛顿
In the very early part of optics, people realized that,
在光学发展的很早期，人们意识到
when you look through the lens of your eye,
你用眼睛通过透镜看东西的时候
the image was up-side down.
图像是上下颠倒的
And there was a lot of argument about
当时有很多的争论说
why that didn't mean you saw things up-side down.
为什么不能是你眼睛平时看见的都是上下颠倒的
So it's sort of the same issue.
这实际上是一样的道理
Reversed from what?
和什么相比反过来了
So we just need some convention.
我们只是需要一个约定
The reason that they're coming at 4, 3 is because we're
它们作为4,3出现的原因是
taking UNEV and consing the result onto argl.
我们从UNEV中取出东西并且cons到了ARGL上面
So you have to realize you've made that convention.
那么你要意识到你已经做了这个约定
The place that you have to realize that--
你需要意识到这点的地方有
well, there's actually two places.
实际上有两个地方
One is in apply-primitive-operator,
第一个在apply-primitive-operator（应用基本操作）这里
which has to realize that the arguments to primitives go in,
你要意识到参数进入基本操作的顺序
in the opposite order from the way you're writing them down.
和你把它们写下来的顺序相反
And the other one is, we'll see later
另一个地方，我们之后会看到
when you actually go to bind a function's parameters,
当你要绑定一个函数的参数的时候
you should realize the arguments are going to come in
你要意识到参数进入的顺序
from the opposite order of the variables to which you're binding them.
和你要绑定这些变量时的顺序相反
So, if you just keep track of that, there's no problem.
所以如果你注意这些，就没有问题了
Also, this is completely arbitrary
同样，这是完全随意的
because, if we'd done, say, an iteration through a vector assigning them,
因为如果我们做了一个，比如，给向量的各个维度赋值的迭代
they might come out in the other order, OK?
它们可能会以其他顺序输出，对吗
So it's just a convention of the way this particular evaluator works.
那么这只是这个求值器工作时的一个约定
All right, let's take a break.
好，我们休息一下
[MUSIC]
教授：我们已经学习了表达式的求值
Professor: We just saw evaluating an expression
虽然这只是一个非常简单的例子
and, of course, that was very simple one. But
但从本质上来说
in essence, it would be no different
它跟那些大型嵌套表达式没什么不同
if it was some big nested expression,
后者只是在栈上递归得更深而已
so there would just be deeper recursion on the stack.
我现在要为你们讲解最后一部分
But what I want to do now is show you the last piece.
#TBD
I want to walk you around this eval and apply loop,
我们还没有仔细研究过它
That's the thing we haven't seen, really.
我们还没有见过一个复合程序
We haven't seen any compound procedures
对它的求值会归约为
where evalutation of procedure reduces to
对一个过程的应用
where applying of procedure reduces to
进而是对过程体的求值
evaluating the body of the procedure,
因此 假设我们有这个
so let's just suppose we had this.
假设我们正在考察
Suppose we were looking at the procedure
(DEFINE (F A B) (+ A B)
define F of A and B to be the sum of A and B.
假设我们预先定义好了这个过程
So, as we typed in that procedure previously,
现在 我们将要求值(F X Y)
and now we're going to evaluate F of X and Y
基于的环境是E0
again, in this environment, E,0,
其中X=3 Y=4
where X is bound to 3 and Y is bound to 4.
当执行DEFINE的时候
When the defined is executed,
还记得么 这里是一个LAMBDA
remember, there's a lambda here,
LAMBDA会创建一个过程
and lambdas create procedures.
基本上 #TBD
And, basically, what will happen is,
在环境E0中 我们会得到F的绑定
in E0, we'll end up with a binding for F,
它指出F是一个过程
which will say F is a procedure,
这个过程的参数是A和B
and its args are A and B,
而过程体是(+ A B)
and its body is plus a,b.
这就是环境大概的样子
So that's what the environment would have looked like
我们之前就定义过了
had we made that definition.
然后 我们去求值(F X Y)
Then, when we go to evaluate F of X and Y,
我会像之前那样 仔细地解释每一步
we'll go through exactly the same process that we did before.
不会跳过重复的表达式
It's even the same expression.
唯一的不同是
The only difference is that
它的内部不再是基本的“+”过程
F, instead of having primitive "plus" in it
它还有这个东西
will have this thing.
因此我们要进行相同的过程
And so we'll go through exactly the same process,
只不过这次 当我们停在APPLY-DISPATCH时
except this time, when we end up at apply-dispatch,
FUN寄存器中不再是基本的“+”过程
the function register, instead of having primitive plus,
而是一个代表过程的东西
will have a thing that will represent it saying procedure,
其中参数为A和B
where the args are A and B,
过程体是(+ A B)
and the body is plus A, B.
再强调一下 我所谓的ENV
And, again, what I mean, by its ENV,
是一个指向环境的指针
I mean there's a pointer to it,
所以不用担心我在这里写了很多东西
so don't worry that I'm writing a lot of stuff there.
这是一个指向代表过程的数据结构的指针
There's a pointer to this procedure data structure.
因此 我们现在面临着相同的情况
OK, so, we're in exactly the same situation.
我们来到了APPLY-DISPATCH
We get to apply-dispatch,
#TBD
so, here, we come to apply-dispatch.
上一次 我们分支跳转到了一个基本过程
Last time, we branched off to a primitive procedure.
然而这一次
Here, it says oh,
我们遇到的是一个复合过程
we now have a compound procedure,
因此我们要跳转到COMPOUND-APPLY
so we're going to go off to compound-apply.
COMPOUND-APPLY又是怎样定义的呢？
Now, what's compound-apply?
还记得元循环求值器是怎么做的么？
Well, remember what the meta-circular evaluator did?
COMPOUND-APPLY的执行步骤则是
Compound-apply said we're going to evaluate
在一个新的环境中
the body of the procedure
求值一个过程的体
in some new environment.
这个新的环境来自于哪里呢？
Where does that new environment come from?
我们把跟过程一同打包的环境
We take the environment that was packaged with the procedure,
我们把过程的形式参数
we bind the parameters of the procedure
同传递进来的实际参数给绑定起来
to the arguments that we're passing in,
把这个作为新的框架
and use that as a new frame to extend
来扩展过程附带的环境
the procedure environment.
我们就是在这个环境中
And that's the environment
求值过程的体
in which we evaluate the procedure body,
对吧？这就是APPLY-EVAL循环做的事
Right? That's going around the apply/eval loop.
这就是APPLY回过头来调用EVAL
That's apply coming back to call eval,
因此 这就是我们要在COMPOUND-APPLY中要做的所有事
So, now, that's all we have to do in compound-apply.
要怎么来实现呢？
What are we going to do?
我们要构造一个新的环境
We're going to manufacture a new environment.
而我们构造的这个新环境呢
And we're going to manufacture a new environment that,
我们把它记作E1
let's see, that we'll call E1.
E1这个环境呢
E1 is going to be some environment where the
存储了过程的参数绑定
where the parameters of the procedure,
其中A=3 B=4
Nwhere A is bound to 3, and B is bound to 4,
并且它跟E0相连
and it's linked to E0
这是因为 F就是在E0中定义的
because that's where f is defined.
因此 在这个环境中
And, in this environment,
我们要来求值过程的体
we're going to evaluate the body of the procedure.
让我们来看一看
So let's look at that, we're going
我们来看COMPOUND-APPLY的代码
Here we are at compound-apply,
首先是给EXP寄存器赋值
which says assign to the expression register
所赋的值是FUN寄存器所指向过程的体
the body of the procedure that's in the function register.
这样 我就将过程的体赋值给了EXP寄存器
So I assign to the expression register the procedure body,
对吧？
OK?
而这将在某个环境中求值
That's going to be evaluated in an environment
这个环境是通过将FUN寄存器
which is formed by making some bindings
所指向的过程中的形式参数
using information determined by the procedure--
与实际参数绑定起来 得到的
that's what's in FUN-- and the argument list.
我们先不要关系它的具体细节
And let's not worry about exactly what that does,
你可以知道它的最后结果
but you can see the information's there.
因此MAKE-BINDINGS会说
So make bindings will say oh,
过程本身就附带有一个环境
the procedure, itself, had an environment attached to it.
在这里 我没有写出来
I didn't write that quite here.
但我应该说过它有一个环境
I should've said in environment
因为每个过程在构造时 都有一个环境
because every procedure gets built with an environment.
因此 通过这个环境 它能够知道
So, from that environment, it knows
定义该过程时的环境是怎样的
what the procedure's definition environment is.
它知道实际参数是什么
It knows what the arguments are.
它查看ARGL
It looks at argl,
然后你会在这里看到逆序的约定
and then you see a reversal convention here.
它需要知道ARGL是逆序的
It just has to know that argl is reversed,
然后它构造了这个框架 E1
and it builds this frame, E,1.
我们假设 MAKE-BINDINGS返回的就是这些东西
All right, so, let's assume that that's what make bindings returns,
然后 它把E1赋值给ENV
so it assigns to ENV this thing, E,1.
下一步就是 恢复CONTINUE
The next thing it says is restore continue.
还记得CONTINUE之前是什么吗？
Remember what continue was here?
在最后一段中
It got put up in the last segment.
CONTINUE被保存了
Continue got stored.
它的值是最初的'DONE
That was the original done,
这代表了
which said what are you going to do
在完成这项特定应用后要做的事
after you're done with this particular application?
这是在求值整个应用时
It was one of the very first things that happened
最先发生的事儿
when we evaluated the application.
现在 我们要恢复CONTINUE了
And now, finally, we're going to restore continue.
还记得APPLY-DISPATCH的约定么？
Remember apply-dispatch's contract.
它假设下一步的跳转目标
It assumes that where it should go to next
已经存放在栈上了
was on the stack,
并且 这里确实存放在栈上了
and there it was on the stack.
CONTINUE被赋值成了DONE
Continue has done,
现在我们要回到EVAL-DISPATCH了
and now we're going to go back to eval-dispatch.
我们要再次进行寄存器设置
We're set up again.
我们有表达式、环境、下一步
We have an expression, an environment, and a place to go to.
我不会再细讲了
We're not going to go through that
因为它基本上就是相同的表达式
because it's sort of the same expression.
但是需要注意的是 在这个时候
OK, but the thing, again, to notice is, at this point,
我们已经归约了原始表达式(F X Y)
we have reduced the original expression, F,X,Y,
通过在E0中求值(F X Y)
We've reduced evaluating F,X,Y in environment E,0
将其归约为在E1中求值(+ A B)
to evaluate plus A, B in E,1.
要注意 栈上并没有什么东西 对吧？
And notice, nothing's on the stack, right?
这是一个归约
It's a reduction.
这个时候 作为其状态的一部分
At this point, the machine does not contain,
#TBD
as part of its state,
the fact that it's in the middle of evaluating some procedure called f,
that's gone, right?
这里面没有积累的状态
Right? There's no accumulated state?
注意 这个思想非常重要
Again, that's a very important idea.
这意味着
That's the meaning of,
当我们使用代换模型时
when we used to write in the substitution model,
一条表达式会归约到另一条表达式
this expression reduces to that expression.
而你不需要记住任何东西
And you don't have to remember anything.
这里 你就见到了归约的真谛
And here, you see the meaning of reduction.
这个时候 栈上没有任何东西
At this point, there is nothing on the stack.
这样就有一个非常重要的结果
See, that has very important consequences.
让我们回过头来看看迭代式阶乘
Let's go back and look at iterative factorial,
还记得吗？这是通过ITER来实现的循环
all right? Remember, this was some sort of loop and doing iter.
我们不断强调 它是一个迭代过程
And we kept saying that's an iterative procedure,
还记得吗
And what we wrote, remember,
我们使用它的时候
are things like, we said,
是像(FACT-ITER 5)这样调用它的
fact-iter of 5.
然后我们把它归约成(ITER 1 1 5)
We wrote things like reduces to iter of 1, and 1, and 5,
然后它归约成(ITER 1 2 5)
which reduces to iter of 1, and 2, and 5,
等等等等
and so on, and so on, and so on.
然后我们又说 看
And we kept saying well, look,
为了实现这个效果 不需要存储任何东西
you don't have to build up any storage to do that.
我们摆了摆手 说
And we waved our hands,
“原则上 这不需要任何存储”
and said in principle, there's no storage needed.
现在你们发现 确实不需要
Now, you see no storage needed.
这里的每一步都是真正的归约 对吧？
Each of these is a real reduction, right?
随着你求值这些表达式
As you walk through these expressions,
在求值这些表达式的过程中 你会发现
As you walk through these expressions, what you'll see
栈上的这些表达式
are these expressions on the stack
都在一个特定的环境中
in some particular environment,
抱歉 是EXP寄存器中的表达式
and then these expressions, sorry, in the EXP register
是在某个特定的环境中
in some particular environment.
并且 在每一步
And, at each point,
栈上不会积累任何东西
there'll be no accumulated stuff on the stack
因为每一步都是真正的归约
because each one's a real reduction.
因此 举例来说
All right, so, for example,
说得更仔细一点
just to go through it in a little bit more care,
如果我从这样的一条表达式开始
if I start out with an expression that says something like,
比如说 在某个环境中计算(FACT-ITER 5)
oh, say, fact-iter of 5 in some environment
它将在某个时刻创建一个环境
that will, at some point, create an environment
其中N=5
in which n is down to 5.
我们把它写下来
Let's call that--
然后 在某个时候
And, at some point,
机器会归约这整个东西
the machine will reduce this whole thing
将它归约为
to a thing that says that's really
(ITER 1 1 N)
iter of 1, and 1, and n,
然后在环境E1中求值这条表达式
evaluated in this environment, E,1
而不在栈上存放任何东西
with nothing on the stack.
看到了么 这时机器并不会记住
See, at this moment, the machine is not remembering
求值这条ITER表达式--
that evaluating this expression, iter--
也就是某种循环--
which is the loop--
并不是FACT-ITER的一部分
is part of this thing called iterative factorial.
它不会记住这个事实
It's not remembering that.
它只是归约了该表达式
It's just reducing the expression to that, right?
如果我们再来看迭代式阶乘的体
If we look again at the body of iterative factorial,
这条表达式归约为了这条表达式
this expression has reduced to that expression.
哦 这里漏了一个N
Oh, I shouldn't have the n there.
幻灯片和实际程序中的约定稍有不同
It's a slightly different convention from the slide to the program.
那么 ITER的体又是什么？
And, then, what's the body of iter?
ITER的体首先是一个IF--
Well, iter's going to be an if,
我不会再深入IF语句的细节了
and I won't go through the details of if.
它会对谓词求值
It'll evaluate the predicate.
本例中 会返回FALSE
In this case, it'll be false.
然后这里的ITER会归约为表达式--
And this iter will now reduce to the expression
(ITER (* COUNTER PRODUCT)
iter of whatever it says, star, counter product, and--
按照它代码写的--
what does it say--
(+ COUNTER 1))
plus counter 1
在另外的一个环境E2中求值
in some other environment, by this time, E,2,
其中 E2会记录着
where E,2 will be set up having bindings
PRODUCT和COUNTER的值
for product and counter.
它会被归约为这条语句
And it'll reduce to that.
它不会记得
Right? It won't be remembering
它是一个需要返回到某处的一部分
that it's part of something that it has to return to.
当ITER再次调用ITER时
And when iter calls iter again,
它会归约为另一个像这样的东西
it'll reduce to another thing that looks like this
只是会在新环境E3中
in some environment, E,3,
里面有关于PRODUCT和COUNTER新的绑定
which has new bindings for product and counter.
因此 如果你想知道
OK? So, if you're wondering,
如果你一直感到不安
if you've always been queasy about
不知道为什么我们说这些过程
about how it is we've been saying those procedures
虽然从语法上看起来是递归的
that look syntactically recursive,
但实际上是迭代的
are, in fact, iterative,
可以在常量空间中运行
run in constant space,
我不知道这么说是否打消了你们的疑虑
well, I don't know if this makes you less queasy,
但至少让你们知道发生了什么
but at least it shows you what's happening.
这其中没有任何构造
There really isn't any buildup there.
但你也会说 这里面还是有一些构造
Now, you might ask well, is there buildup
从原则上来说 我们也构造了环境框架
in principle in these environment frames?
答案则是
And the answer is yeah,
你确实需要构建这些环境框架
you have to make these new environment frames,
但是 等你求值完毕后不必保留它们
but you don't have to hang onto them when you're done.
它们可以被废料收集
They can be garbage collected,
这些空间也可以被自动地重用
or the space can be reused automatically.
但你们可以看到求值器控制流
But you see the control structure of the evaluator
的中心思想就是进行归约
is really using this idea that you actually have a reduction,
因此这些过程实际上是迭代过程
so these procedures really are iterative procedures.
好吧 有什么问题么？
All right, let's stop for questions.
好吧 课件休息吧
All right, let's break.
[音乐]
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
跟迭代过程形成对比的
Let me contrast the iterative procedure
是确实会占用空间的递归过程
just so you'll see where space does build up with a recursive procedure,
你们可以看到其中的区别
so you can see the difference.
让我们来看看递归式阶乘的求值
Let's look at the evaluation of recursive factorial.
这里的FACT-REC就是阶乘的标准定义
So, here's fact-recursive, or standard factorial definition.
这个当然是一个递归过程
We said this one is still a recursive procedure,
它的计算过程也是递归的
but this is actually a recursive process.
然后 只要把它和我们开始的方式联系起来
And then, just to link it back to the way we started,
我们会通过代换模型发现
we said oh, you can see that it's going to be recursive process
这是一个递归过程
by the substitution model
因为 如果我调用(REC-FACT 5)
because, if I say recursive factorial of 5,
会变成(* 5
that turns into 5 times--
哦 这里是FACT-REC
what is it, fact-rec, or record fact--
(* 5 (FACT-REC 4))
5 times recursive factorial of 4,
又会变成(* 5 (* 4 (FACT-REC 3)))
which turns into 5 times 4 times fact-rec of 3,
又会变成(* 5 (* 4 (* 3 (* ...
which returns into 5 times 4 times 3 times
以此类推
and so on, right?
关键点就是 有一条链条被不断构造出来
The idea is there was this chain of stuff building up,
这就在代换模型中证明了
which justified, in the substitution model,
FACT-REC是递归的
the fact that it's recursive.
现在 让我们来看看这条构造起来的链条
And now, let's actually see that chain of stuff build up
它又是在机器中的什么地方？
and where it is in the machine, OK?
好吧 让我们想象一下要从哪里开始
All right, well, let's imagine we're going to start out again.
我们告诉机器 求值(FACT-REC 5)
We'll tell it to evaluate recursive factorial of 5
基于的环境是E0
in some environment, again, E0, where
也就是定义FACT-REC时的环境
where recursive factorial is defined, OK?
现在 我们知道最终要发生什么
Well, now we know what's eventually going to happen.
首先
This is going to come along,
它会对这些东西求值
it'll evaluate those things,
发现它是一个过程
figure out it's a procedure,
在这里创建一个新环境E1
build somewhere over here an environment, E1,
其中N=5
which has n bound to 5,
并且与E0相连
which hangs off of E0,
这个E0也就是
which would be, presumably,
定义FACT-REC的那个环境
the definition environment of recursive factorial.
然后 在E1这个环境中
OK? And, in this environment,
求值过程的体
it's going to go off and evaluate the body.
因此 在这里求值会归约为
So, again, the evaluation here will reduce to
在E1中求值过程的体
evaluating the body in E1.
这就需要求值IF语句
That's going to look at an if,
而我不会讲解IF语句的细节
and I won't go through the details of if.
IF语句会求值谓词
It'll look at the predicate.
最后发现需要求值ELSE子句
It'll decide it eventually has to evaluate the alternative.
因此 这里的整个部分 会归约为
So this whole thing, again, will reduce to
FACT-REC的ELSE子句
the alternative of recursive factorial,
也就是谓词为假的部分
the alternative clause,
整个表达式就归约为了(* N
which says that this whole thing reduces to times n
(FACT-REC (- N 1))
of recursive factorial of n minus 1
求值的环境是E1
in the environment E1
因此 最初的表达式现在就会归约为
OK? So the original expression, now, is going to reduce
求值这样的一个表达式
to evaluating that expression, all right?
而现在 我们面对的是一个应用
OK? Now we have an application.
我们之前求值过应用
We did an application before.
还记得要怎么求值应用么？
Remember what happens in an application?
正式求值一个应用之前
The first thing you do is you go off and you
你需要把CONTINUE寄存器的值保存在栈上
you save the value of the continue register on the stack.
此时 栈上会有一个值'DONE
So the stack here is going to have done in it.
接下来 你要为求值子部分做准备
And then you're going to set up to evaluate the sub-parts.
因此 我们在这里开始求值子部分
OK? So here we go off to evaluate the sub-parts.
首先要做的是求值运算符
First thing we're going to do is evaluate the operator.
运算符是怎样求值的呢？
What happens when we evaluate an operator?
我们通过一些手段
Well, we arrange things so that
将EXP寄存器指向运算符对应的过程
the operator ends up in the expression register.
并且让ENV寄存器指向求值的环境
The environments in the ENV register
#TBD
continue someplace where we're going to go evaluate the arguments.
并且 我们把
And, on the stack,
CONTINUE的原始值保存在栈上
we've saved the original continue,
我们完成所有工作后 就会跳转到这个地方
which is where we wanted to be when we're all done.
在我们求值完运算符后
And then the things we needed
需要做的则是
when we're going to get done evaluating the operator,
求值对实际参数进行求值
the things we'll need to evaluate the arguments,
也就是这个环境和这些参数
namely the environment and those arguments,
这些尚未求值的实际参数
those unevaluated arguments,
它们现在都还在栈上
so there they are sitting on the stack.
我们现在就要先来求值运算符
And we're about to go off to evaluate the operator.
当我们从这个调用返回时
Well, when we return from this particular call--
在这里 我们将要去调用EVAL-DISPATCH
so we're about to call eval-dispatch here--
当我们从这个调用返回时
when we return from this call,
这个运算符所对应的值
the value of that operator,
在本例中 也就是基本的乘法过程
which, in this case, is going to be the primitive multiplier procedure,
会存放在FUN寄存器中
will end up in the FUN register.
我们要去求值实际参数
We're going to evaluate some arguments.
现在这里求值N
They will evaluate n here.
本例中 会返回5
That'll give us 5, in this case.
然后我们会把它放入ARGL寄存器
We're going to put that in the argl register,
然后我们会去求值第二个运算对象
and then we'll go off to evaluate the second operand.
就在我们准备求值第二个运算对象之时
So, at the point where we go off to evaluate the second operand--
我会省略计算(- N 1)之类的细节
and I'll skip details like computing, and minus 1, and all of that--
但是 当我们去求值第二个运算对象时
but, when we go off to evaluate the second operand,
会最终归约为对FACT-REC的另一个调用
that will eventually reduce to another call to fact-recursive.
现在 我们在栈上有
And, what we've got on the stack here is
来自于这个组合式的运算符
the operator from that combination that we're going to use it in
以及其它的参数
and the other argument.
现在 我们已经准备好
OK? So, now, we're set up for another call
去调用另外的FACT-REC了
to recursive factorial.
而让我们完成了这个调用以后
And, when we're done with this one,
我们就要跳转到ACCUMULATE-LAST-ARG
we're going to go to accumulate the last arg.
还记得这是做什么的么？
and remember what that'll do?
它会说
That'll say oh,
我们会把这个调用的结果
whatever the result of this has to get combined with that,
和这个5相乘
and we're going to multiply them.
但是请注意
But, notice now,
我们现在处于另一个递归阶乘中
we're at another recursive factorial.
我们又要再次调用EVAL-DISPATCH
We're about to call eval-dispatch again,
然而我们并没有真正地“归约”它
except we haven't really reduced it
因为现在栈上还有东西
because there's stuff on the stack now.
栈上的这些东西说：“当你返回时”
The stuff on the stack says oh, when you get back,
你最好把结果和放在这里的5相乘
you'd better multiply it by the 5 you had hanging there.
所以当我们进行另外的调用
So, when we go off to make another call,
求值(- N 1)
we evaluate the n minus 1.
这会返回给我们另一个环境
That gives us another environment which
其中N的新值为4
in which the new n's going to be down to 4.
然后又将调用EVAL-DISPATCH
And we're about to call eval-dispatch again.
我们又创建了另一个调用
We get another call.
这个4又会遇到相同的情况
That 4 is going to end up in the same situation.
我们最后会遇到对(FACT-REC N)的又一次调用
We'll end up with another call to fact-recursive n.
而这时候 栈上会有从最初的调用
And sitting on the stack will be the stuff from the original one
#TBD
and, now, the subsidiary one we're doing.
它们都在等待同一个东西
And both of them are waiting for the same thing.
它们都要跳转到ACCUMULATE-LAST-ARG
They're going to go to accumulate a last argument.
当然 当我们进行第四次调用时
And then, of course, when we go to the fourth call,
会发生同样的事
the same thing happens.
如此往复
And this goes on, and on, and on.
在这里 你在栈上看到的
And what you see here on the stack,
#TBD
exactly what's sitting here on the stack,
the thing that says times and 5.
而你要把它用来
And what you're going to do with that
乘以最后一个实参
accumulate that into a last argument.
#TBD
That's exactly this, right?
这正是这些东西#TBD
This is exactly where that stuff is hanging.
实际上 你将要应用的运算符
Effectively, the operator you're going to apply,
以及其它的参数
the other argument that it's got to be multiplied by when you get back
#TBD
when you get back and the parentheses,
which says yeah, what you wanted to do was accumulate them.
#TBD
So, you see, the substitution model is not such a lie.
从某种意义上来说 它实际上是
That really is, in some sense,
存在于栈上的那些东西
what's sitting right on the stack.
好吧 从某种意义上来说
All right, so that,
应该给你们解释了
in some sense, should explain for you,
或者 至少让你们相信
or at least convince you,
求值器会通过某些方式
that somehow, this evaluator is managing
迭代地去求值某些过程
to take these procedures and execute some of them iteratively
而递归地去求值另外的过程
and some of them recursively,
尽管从语法上看
even though, as syntactically,
它们都是递归过程
they look like recursive procedures.
它又是如何做到的呢？
How's it managing to do that?
其中的基本原因就是
Well, the basic reason it's managing to do that
求值器被设置为
is the evaluator is set up
只保存那些稍后会用到的东西
to save only what it needs later.
比如说 当你在把
So, for example, at the point where you've reduced
在一个环境中求值表达式归约为
evaluating an expression and an environment
将某个过程应用在参数上时
to applying a procedure to some arguments,
它就不再需要最初的环境了
it doesn't need that original environment anymore
因为所需要的环境信息都被打包到
because any environment stuff will be packaged inside the procedures
需要应用的那个过程中了
where the application's going to happen.
同样 类似地
All right, similarly,
当你求值一个参数表时
when you're going along evaluating an argument list,
当你完成对表的求值时
when you've finished evaluating the list,
当你求值完最后一个参数时
when you're finished evaluating the last argument,
你就不再需要这个参数表了 对吧？
you don't need that argument list any more, right?
你也就不再需要
And you don't need the environment where
求值这些参数所需的环境了
those arguments would be evaluated.
所以这个解释器如此“智能”的根本原因
So the basic reason that this interpreter is being so smart
根本不是因为它“智能” 只是因为它老实
is that it's not being smart at all, it's being stupid.
它的原则就是：“只保存那些需要的”
It's just saying I'm only going to save what I really need.
这里 让我来给你们展示
Well, let me show you here.
这是致使尾递归的根本原因
Here's the actual thing that's making a tail recursive.
要记住 (RESOTRE CONTINUE)这条代码
Remember, it's the restore of continue.
它指的是 当我去求值过程体的时候
It's saying when I go off to evaluate the procedure body,
我应该告诉EVAL返回到
I should tell eval to come back to
最初的求值
the place where that original
应该返回的地方
evaluation was supposed to come back to.
因此 从某种角度来说
So, in some sense,
你想知道是哪一行代码致使了尾递归
you want to say what's the actual line that makes tail recursive
那么就是这一行
It's that one.
出于某些奇怪的原因
If I wanted to build a non-
如果我想构建一个没有尾递归的求值器
tail recursive evaluator, for some strange reason,
我需要做的就是
all I would need to do
在这里先不要去恢复CONTINUE
is, instead of restoring continue at this point,
而是在这里建立一个标签
I'd set up a label down here
用来标识完成过程应用后的返回位置
called, "Where to come back after you've finished applying the procedure."
而我会把CONTINUE设置为这个标签
Instead, I'd set continue to that.
然后跳转到EVAL-DISPATCH
I'd go to eval-dispatch,
然后EVAL-DISPATCH会回到这里
and then eval-dispatch would come back here.
而这时
At that point,
我会恢复CONTINUE
I would restore continue
并回到最初的返回位置
and go to the original one.
因此 这里唯一的后果就是
So here, the only consequence of that
解释器不再是尾递归的了
would be to make it non-tail recursive.
它会给你完全相同的答案
It would give you exactly the same answers,
只是当你执行迭代式阶乘
except if you did that iterative factorial
或者其它迭代过程时
and all those iterative procedures,
它都会递归地去执行
it would execute recursively.
然而 我对你们撒了一个小谎
Well, I lied to you a little bit, but just a little bit,
因为我演示的
because I showed you a slightly
一个有些过于简化的解释器
over-simplified evaluator
这个解释器假设每个过程
where it assumes that each procedure --
只含有一条表达式
each procedure body has only one expression.
还记得吗 通常来说
Remember, in general,
过程的体是多条表达式组成的序列
a procedure has a sequence of expressions in it.
所以没有什么新概念
So there's nothing really conceptually new.
让我来展示一下实际的求值器
Let me just show you the actual evaluator
是怎么来处理表达式序列的
that handles sequences of expressions.
这是现在的COMPOUND-APPLY
This is compound-apply now,
和之前的唯一不同是
and the only difference from the old one
它不再直接地跳转到EVAL
is that, instead of going off to eval directly,
它先获取整个过程的体
it takes the whole body of the procedure,
在本例中 也就是表达式序列
which, in this case, is a sequence of expressions,
然后跳转到EVAL-SEQUENCE
and goes off to eval-sequence.
EVAL-SEQUENCE是一个小型的循环
And eval-sequence is a little loop
然后每次求值一条表达式
that, basically, does these evaluations one at a time.
就是这样来求值的--
So it does an evaluation.
当它求值完一条表达式后
Says oh, when I come back,
会跳转到这里 去求值下一条
I'd better come back here to do the next one.
当我完成了所有的求值后
And, when I'm all done,
我想要跳转到LAST-EXP
when I want to get the last expression,
我就只需要恢复CONTINUE寄存器
I just restore my continue
然后跳转到EVAL-DISPATCH
and go off to eval-dispatch.
同样的 如果你想要在这种求值器中
And, again, if you wanted for some reason
破坏尾递归机制
to break tail recursion in this evaluator,
你只需要在LAST-EXP中不做特殊处理即可
all you need to do is not handle the last expression, especially.
也就是说 当你处理完最后一条表达式
Just say, after you've done the last expression,
你跳转到另外一个地方
come back to some other place
在那个地方去恢复CONTINUE
after which you restore continue.
出于某些原因
And, for some reason,
很多Lisp求值器倾向于这么做
a lot of LISP evaluators tended to work that way.
这样做的后果就是
And the only consequence of that is that
迭代式过程也会使栈增长
iterative procedures built up stack.
还不清楚为什么会这样
And it's not clear why that happened.
好吧 我稍微来总结一下
All right. Well, let me just sort of summarize,
毕竟这是一个大程序
since this is a lot of details
又有很多细节
in a big program.
但关键点就是
But the main point is that
#TBD
it's no different, conceptually, from translating any other program.
核心思想就是
And the main idea is that
我们已经有了通用求值器程序
we have this universal evaluator program,
一个元循环求值器
the meta-circular evaluator.
如果我们把它翻译为了Lisp
If we translate that into LISP,
那么我们就有了Lisp的所有东西
then we have all of LISP.
我们就是这么来做的
And that's all we did.
第二点则是 魔法消失了
The second point is that the magic's gone away.
这整个系统不再神秘了 对吧？
There should be no more magic in this whole system, right?
原则上来说 这应该相当清楚了
In principle, it should all be very clear
只是还不太了解表结构的内存管理
except, maybe, for how list structured memory works,
我们后面会讲
and we'll see that later.
这也并不困难
But that's not very hard.
第三点就是
The third point is that
所有的这些尾递归
all this tail recursion
来自于严格的求值纪律
came from the discipline of eval being very careful
也就是只保存那些后面会用到的东西
to save only what it needs next time.
而不是一些比较随意的原则
It's not some arbitrary thing
比如 无论什么时候我们调用一个子过程
where we're saying well, whenever we call a sub-routine,
我们会保存所有的寄存器并且返回
we'll save all the registers in the world and come back?
有些时候为了提效 这样做很值得
See, sometimes it pays to really worry about efficiency.
当你研究求值机器的内部原理时
And, when you're down in the guts of your evaluator machine,
这类东西就很值得去研究
it really pays to think about things like that
因为它会带来显著的不同
because it makes big consequences.
我想现在基本上已经
Well, I hope what this has done
把这个求值器讲得很清楚了
is really made the evaluator seem concrete.
我希望你们能相信
I hope you really believe
真的有人能够
that somebody could hold a LISP
将一个Lisp求值器放在掌心之中
LISP evaluator in the palm of their hand.
为了让你们死心塌地
Maybe to help you believe that, here's a
我给你们看一个Lisp求值器
here's a LISP evaluator
它就在我的手掌中
that I'm holding the palm of my hand.
这块求值器芯片实际上
And this is a chip which is actually
比我给你们展示的求值器还要复杂
quite a bit more complicated than the evaluator I showed you.
这张图片效果更好
Uh.. maybe, here's a better picture of it.
在这上面
What there is,
你可以看到相同的宏观结构
is you can see the same overall structure.
这是寄存器阵列
This is a register array.
这些是数据通路
These are the data paths.
这里有是有穷状态控制器
Here's a finite state controller.
再强调一下 是有穷状态
And again, finite state,
全都在这里了
that's all there is.
在另外的地方还有外部存储
And somewhere there's external memory
用来存储数据
that'll worry about things.
而这块芯片非常复杂
And this particular one is very complicated
是因为它尝试更快地运行Lisp
because it's trying to run LISP fast.
它具有非常非常之快的并行运算
And it has some very, very fast parallel operations in there
比如说 如果你想要索引一个数组
like, if you want to index into an array,
同时又要检查该索引是否为一个整数
simultaneously check that the index is an integer,
以及该索引没有越界
check that it doesn't exceed the array bands,
同时还要进行内存存取
and go off and do the memory access,
它会同时进行这些事
and do all those things simultaneously.
如果这些操作都没有问题的话
And then, later, if they're all OK,
最终就会在这里得到结果
actually get the value there.
因此 数据通路中大量的
So there are a lot of complicated operations
复杂运算使得Lisp能够并行运行
in these data paths for making LISP run in parallel.
这完全是一种求值Lisp的无冒险的哲学#TBD
It's a completely non-risk philosophy of evaluating LISP.
并且 这个的微指令也相当复杂
And then, this microcode is pretty complicated.
让我先看一看
Let's see, there's what?
这其中有大概389条
There's about 389 instructions of
220比特的微指令
of 220-bit microcode sitting here
只因为这些数据通路非常复杂
because these are very complicated data paths.
整个芯片大概有89,000支晶体管
And the whole thing has about 89,000 transistors, OK?
好吧 我希望通过这节课解答了大部分疑惑
OK. Well, I hope that that takes away a lot of the mystery.
也许你们想看一看这块芯片
Maybe somebody wants to look at this.
好吧 先讲到这里
OK. Let's stop.
有问题吗？
Questions?
学生：您所讲的 听起来像是
AUDIENCE: OK, now, it sounds like what you're saying is that,
如果把(RESTORE CONTINUE)放在合适的地方
with the restore continue put in the proper place,
这样之前递归求值的过程
that procedures that would invoke a recursive process
现在就会变成迭代求值的
now invoke an iterative process
#TBD
just by the way that the eval signature is?
教授：我想我应该这么来说
PROFESSOR: I think the way I'd prefer to put it is that,
如果把(RESTORE CONTINUE)放在了错误的位置
with restore continue put in the wrong place,
你就会让那些语法上看起来像递归的过程
you can cause any syntactically-looking recursive procedure,
在运行的时候不断地扩张栈
in fact, to build up stack as it runs.
但这样是没有原因的
But there's no reason for that,
你可以自己去试一试
so you might want to play around with it.
你可以在COMPOND-APPLY返回后
You can just switch around two or three instructions
交换两、三条语句的顺序
in the way compound-apply comes back,
那么你得到的就不再是尾递归了
and you'll get something which isn't tail recursive.
我只是想强调
But the thing I wanted to emphasize
这其中没有什么魔法
is there's no magic. there's no
这并不是
It's not as if
有什么智能的预处理程序
there's some very clever pre-processing program
它会分析FACT-ITER这个程序
that's looking at this procedure, factorial iter,
然后说
and say oh, gee, um
我注意到
I really notice that
完成这个调用 不需要我进行压栈
I don't have to push stack in order to do this.
但是有些人是这么认为的
Some people think that that's what's going on.
而是一种比这个还要蠢的机制
It's something much, much more dumb than that,
就是在合适的地方插入RESTORE指令
it's this one place you're putting the restore instruction.
就可以自动地实现
It's just automatic.
学生：但这不会影响到时间复杂度 对吧？
AUDIENCE: But that's not affecting the time complexity is it?
教授：不会
PROFESSOR: No.
学生：它不会迭代地处理
AUDIENCE: It's just that it's handling it recursively
而是会递归地处理
instead of iteratively.
但就从完成这两个运算的时间来说
But, in terms of the order of time it takes to finish the operation,
它们都是相同的 对吧？
it's the same one way or the other, right?
教授 ：是的
PROFESSOR: Yes.
尾递归不会改变任何东西的时间复杂度
Tail recursion is not going to change the time complexity of anything
因为 从某种意义上来说
because, in some sense,
两者都是相同的算法
it's the same algorithm that's going on.
它只是让这个过程迭代地运行
What it's doing is really making this thing run as an iteration.
这样 当参数很大时
Right? Not going to run out of memory
它不会耗尽所有的内存
you know counting up to a giant number
因为这其中没有压栈
simply because the stack would get pushed.
事实上 你们需要相信
See, the thing you really have to believe is that,
当我们编写--
when we write--
我们一直把这些代码称作“迭代”
see, we've been writing all these things called iterations,
把(DEFINE (LOOP) (LOOP))称作无穷循环
infinite loops, define loop to be called loop.
这就是一个迭代
That's is as much an iteration
跟我们用DO语句来写无穷循环是一样的
you know as if we wrote do forever loop.
它们只是语法上不同而已
It's just syntactic sugar as the difference.
它们实际上都是迭代
These things are real, honest to god, iterations?
它们并不改变时间复杂度
They don't change the time complexity,
但是它会把它们变成真正的迭代
but they turn them into real iterations.
好吧 下课
All right, thank you.